Walter I. Wardwell Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Walter I. Wardwell Papers.
1946-1984.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Wardwell, Walter I.
4.4 linear feet.
In 1949, Wardwell was appointed instructor in the Department of Sociology at the University of Connecticut. He was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1952 and to Professor in 1966. He retired in 1984 after a 35 year teaching career at the University.
MSS19900018
Biography
Walter I. Wardwell was born in Boston, Massachusetts, on 23 August 1918. He attended Harvard University (A.B., 1940; M.A., 1947; Ph.D., 1951). During World War II, Wardwell served as Assistant Professor of Military Science at M.I.T. and Tufts College Medical School. He also served as Commandant of the Army Specialized Training Unit (ASTU) at Tufts.
In 1949, Wardwell was appointed instructor in the Department of Sociology at the University of Connecticut. He was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1952 and to Professor in 1966. He retired in 1984 after a 35 year teaching career at the University.
During Wardwell's years with the Department of Sociology, he served on numerous University committees, including the Growth and Development Committee of the University Senate, the Environmental Studies Task Force, and the Housing Policy Committee, of which he was chairman. He has been an active member of the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) since 1952 and was president of the University of Connecticut Chapter from 1954 to 1955. He has also served as chairman of the Contract Committee for the University chapter.
Wardwell's fields of specialization are socal organizations and institutions, medical sociology, and sociology of the professions. He has authored numerous journal articles and his essays have appeared in several books on the sociology of helath and of the professions. Wardwell has served as a consultant to the Heart Disease Control Programs and the Division of Medical Care Administration of the U.S. Public Health Service.
Scope and Content
The Wardwell Papers reflect Dr. Wardwell's interests and activities during his tenure at the University and include correspondence, minutes, reports, notes, newspaper clippings, brochures, publications, and fliers. Of particular interest are the materials in Series III: Campus Unrest, documenting some of the campus disturbances of the late 1960s and early 1970s.
Arrangement
Series I: Committees ( 1946-1986 ) consists of committee minutes and reports, related correspondence, notes and newspaper clippings collected by Wardwell during his tenure. Memoranda and correspondence regarding University procdures and policies are also included in the series. Files are arranged alphabetically by committee name.
Series II: Organizations ( 1948-1984 ) consists of materials collected by Wardwell from teachers' unions and other origanizations to which he belonged. Materials in this series include minutes, correspondence, brochures, notes and newspaper clippings. The bulk of the material is related to the AAUP, University of Connecticut Chapter. Materials from the Federation of University Teachers, the Faculty Chapter of the Connecticut Employees Association, and the Faculty for Rational Alternatives are also included. Files are organized alphabetically by subject headings; general AAUP material is arranged chronologically.
Series III: Campus Unrest ( 1968-1975 ) contains material related to the campus disturbances of the late 1960s and early 1970s. Materials in this series inlcude brochures, flyers, reports, correspondence, and newspaper clippings concerning student and faculty unrest at the University of Connecticut. Brochures and newsletters from other universities and agencies are also included. Files are arranged alphabetically by format.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. See especially, American Association of University Professors, University of Connecticut Chapter Records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
American Association of University Professors. University of Connecticut Chapter.; Connecticut State Employees Association. Faculty Chapter.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut. University Senate.; Faculty for Rational Alternatives.; University of Connecticut—Faculty.; Sociology—Study and teaching—Connecticut.; College teachers—Societies, etc.; College students—Connecticut.; Student movements—Connecticut.; Protest movements—Connecticut.; College students—Political activity.; Universities and colleges—Connecticut.; Universities and colleges—Societies, etc.; Educators—Connecticut.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Administrative Records.; Minutes.; Fliers. [printed matter]
Occupations:
Sociologist. Educator.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Wardwell donated his materials in 1984.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Committees, 1946-1986
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Proposals of ROTC Subcommittee (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Arts & Sciences committee on introductory courses, 1954 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Calendar revision committee of the Senate Growth and Development Committee, 1961-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 3-4)
  - Committee on Curricula and Courses, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Doctor of Arts degree Committee of the Graduate faculty, 1970-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Task Force, 1970-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 7-8)
  - Faculty Parking Committee, 1961-1967 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - General, 1946-1979 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Graduate School faculty, Executive Committee, 1960-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Growth & Development Committee, University Senate, 1964-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 12-13)
  - Housing Policy Ccommittee, 1969-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 14-15)
  - Institute of Urban Research, Faculty Advisory Committee, 1963-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Job Placement Committee, College of Arts and Sciences, 1957 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Robert L. Kantor Memorial Committee Records, undated, 1977-1986 (Box 1)
  - School of Education Committee on Curricula and Courses, 1952-1963 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - UConn Foundation Steering Committee, H.D. Babbidge Special Resources Fund, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - University Policies and Procedures, 1950-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - University Senate, Special Committee on Reorganization, 1972-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - University Study Committee: HMO, 1972-1973 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
- Series II: Organizations, 1948-1984
  - American Association of University Professors, UConn Chapter (Box 2)
    - General, 1951-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 23-34)
    - Arbitration, 1977-1981 (Box 3:, Folder 35-36)
    - Board of Higher Education, 1977-1980 (Box 3:, Folder 37)
    - Budget and dues, 1975-1980 (Box 3:, Folder 38)
    - Collective bargaining, 1972-1984 (Box 3:, Folder 39-41)
    - Committee “w”, 1981-1983 (Box 3:, Folder 42)
    - Compensation and committee “z”, 1975-1979 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
    - Connecticut State College newsletter, 1976 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
    - Constitution and by-laws, 1976-1980 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
    - Contract questionnaire, 1978-1980 (Box 3:, Folder 46)
    - Economic status committee, 1977-1981 (Box 3:, Folder 47)
    - Grievance procedures, 1976-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 48-49)
    - Negotiations, 1978-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 50)
    - Non-tenure track faculty, 1976-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 51)
    - Part-time faculty, 1976-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
    - Personnel procedures, task force, 1975-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 53)
    - Political action state conference, 1975-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 54)
    - Professional development, 1978-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 55)
    - Retirement committee and pensions, 1978-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 56)
    - Sabbatical and other leaves, 1977-1978 (Box 4:, Folder 57)
    - Speakers, 1976 (Box 4:, Folder 58)
    - Subcommittees, 1975-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 59)
    - Summer session negotiations, 1977-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 60)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1975-1983 (Box 4:, Folder 61-62)
  - Connecticut Employees Association, Faculty Chapter, 1948 (Box 4:, Folder 63)
  - Faculty for Rational Alternatives, 1975-1982 (Box 4:, Folder 64)
  - Federation of University Teachers, Local 1386, 1961-1982 (Box 4:, Folder 65)
  - Graduate Student Council, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 66)
- Series III: Campus Unrest, 1968-1975
  - Flyers, brochures and announcements, 1968-1970s (Box 5:, Folder 67)
  - Memoranda, correspondence and reports, 1968-1975 (Box 5:, Folder 68-70)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1968-1974 (Box 5:, Folder 71-72)
  - Non UConn brochures and newsletters, 1968-1970s (Box 5:, Folder 73)
  - The Black Panther, AIM Bulletin, Guardian, 1968-1970 (Box 5:, Folder 74)
  - The Revolution (cont): At the University of Connecticut, 1969 (Box 5:, Folder 75)